Register of the Peter Oslin Hefron papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Peter Oslin Hefron papers
1961-2005
2010C12
Hefron, Peter Oslin, 1945-
12 manuscript boxes, 4 phonorecords. (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers contain materials relating to American military activities during the Vietnam War, including a memoir, propaganda leaflets, other printed matter, and photographs. Also includes photographs of postwar Vietnam; and photographs, postcards, guidebooks, and other printed matter relating to war monuments and other historical monuments and museums in various countries of Asia and Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Hefron was a private first class in the United States Army, serving as a member of the 90th Replacement Battalion from 1969 to 1970, and professor of political science at Troy State University, Pacific Region, and European Region.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers contain materials relating to American military activities during the Vietnam War, including a memoir, propaganda leaflets, other printed matter, and photographs. They include photographs of postwar Vietnam; and photographs, postcards, guidebooks, and other printed matter relating to war monuments and other historical monuments and museums in various countries of Asia and Europe.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States.--Army.--Replacement Battalion, 90th.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Propaganda.; Vietnam--Pictorial works.; War memorials.; Phonorecords
Collection Contents
- Vietnam file, 1961-2005 (Box 1-5)
  Includes memoir, psychological warfare leaflets, collected materials, and photographs. Arranged by format.
  - "Memories of a U.S. Army Replacement Battalion: Service and Disservice to the Vietnam War Effort," by Peter O. Hefron, Ph.D. Unpublished typescript, 2005 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Psychological warfare leaflets (Box 1)
    - North Vietnam (Box 1)
      - "U.S. Officers and Men in the 25th Infantry Division" (Folder 1: 2)
      - "Officers and Men in the 1st Air Cav. Div."; "G.I.'s in Dongdu Basecamp!"(2) (Folder 1: 3)
      - "Letter of 3 U.S. P.O.Ws to drivers in the U.S. Army in S.V.N.," "Letter of 3 US P.O.Ws to G.I.s in South [sic] V.N." (2) (Folder 1: 4)
      - "P.O.W. Smith to G.I's"; "Impression of US Released P.O.W"; "Rallied Man Nolan to 1st and 25th Infantrymen!" (3) (Folder 1: 5)
      - "Letter of a Colored P.O.W. to Colored G.I.s in S.V.N."; "Where is the Battlefield of Colored Americans?" (4) (Folder 1: 6)
      - "Toll Bigger Than Last Year"; "When Will Your Turn Be?"; "Repatriate or Die!" (Folder 1: 7)
      - "U.S. Officers and GIs!"; "Welcome to G.I.s Opposing the US Imperialist Aggressive War in South Vietnam?" (3) (Folder 1: 8)
      - "American GIs"; "Officers and Men in the US Armed Forces in South VN!" (2) (Folder 1: 9)
      - "Early End to the Vietnam War, American Troops Back Home Now"; "U.S. Servicemen!" (2) (Folder 1: 10)
      - "G.I.s, Refuse to go out fighting an dying for the capitalist gun-dealers and the rotten puppets in Saigon"; "Put down the corrupt puppet administration of Thiê u-Ky-Huon?"; "Peace of Vietnam, Bring Americans Home." (3) (Folder 1: 11)
      - "The 10 point over-all solution of the SVNNLF to the South Vietnam problem helps restore peace in V.N."; "American G.I's" (2) (Folder 1: 12)
      - "Why???"; "Early end to the Vietnam war, American troops back home now!" (2) (Folder 1: 13)
      - "Hey, Hey LBJ, How many kids did you kill today?"; "American GI's!" (2) (Folder 1: 14)
      - "American Servicemen!"; "The US should immediately begin pulling its troops out of Vietnam with all possible speed" (3) (Folder 1: 15)
      - "What's in Washington's war for you?"; "Senator Wayne Morse (AP April 29, 1967)"; "Do you know?" (3) (Folder 1: 16)
      - "American officers and men" [1 laminated leaflet] (Folder 1: 17)
      - "U.S. Army in South Vietnam! [photocopy] (Folder 1: 18)
    - South Vietnam and the United States (Box 1)
      - "Chiêu Hồi-The Winning Ticket (MACV Command Information Pamphlet 6-68, July 1968)" (3) (Box 1: 19)
      - "'Chiêu Hồi' mang lai cho bạn một đời sống tự dọ và hạnh phúc (4-23-69)"; "Một thưỏng dân đang nộp...(6-400-69)"; "Hãy trở về trong danh...(2756)" (4) (Folder 1: 20)
      - "Hồi Chánh thật là dễ dàng (2632)"; "Chiêu Hồi-The Winning Ticket"; "Chiêu Hồi, Chiêu Hồi, dấu vũ-khí" (6-361-68). (6) (Folder 1: 21)
      - "Bạn có biết sự thật? (2380);" (7) (Folder 1: 22)
      - "Làm sao đễ đứợc an-toàn? (6-194-69) (6) (Folder 1: 23)
      - "Ðừng đợi đến khi... (147-66-R)"; "Ðây phóng pháo cơ khõng lồ B.52" (146-66-1); "Chính phủ muốn đồng..." (SP-2316). (3) (Folder 1: 24)
      - "Lòng nhân đạo..." (3040). (1) (Folder 1: 25)
      - "Các bạn cán bộ" (3041). (1) (Folder 1: 26)
      - "Giấy thông-hành." (3) (Folder 1: 27)
      - "Saigon đẹp lấm" (4-15-69). (1) (Folder 1: 28)
      - "Anh hãy về đây..." (3488); "Đồng bào miền nam..." (3494). (2) (Folder 1: 29)
      - "Các bạn cán-binh trong hang ngữ Việt-Cộng" (SP-1380). (1) (Folder 1: 30)
      - "Các bạn cán-binh trong M.T.G.P. chú ý!!" (6-443-68). (1) (Folder 1: 31)
      - "Có phải những người này..." (SP-1415); "Cùng các bạn cán binh..." (3501). (1) (Folder 1: 32)
      - "Cùng các bạn chiến sĩ từ bác vào nam" (2547). (1) (Folder 1: 33)
      - Clippings about psychological warfare (Folder 1: 34)
  - Other collected material/subject files, 1961-1979 (Box 1)
    - Anti-Vietnam war pamphlets, collected in and around Boston, 1970-1973 (Folder 1: 35)
    - Bombing of Vietnam (Folder 1: 36)
    - Campaign against drug abuse and prostitutes, U.S. military (Folder 1: 37)
    - Combat humor, material produced by U.S. Army personnel (Folder 1: 38)
    - Elections, Republic of Vietnam (South), pamphlets, 1967 and undated (Folder 1: 39)
    - Legal basis for U.S. intervention in Vietnam (copies of documents), 1954-1964; U.S.-North Vietnam peace agreement (photocopy), 1973 (Folder 1: 40)
    - Maps of Vietnam, issued by U.S. Army (Folder 1: 41)
    - Miscellany, U.S. Armed Forces: "Code of Conduct" card, military payment certificates, Geneva Convention identification card, U.S. postage stamp (1979) with explanation of Vietnam Service Medal attached (Folder 1: 42)
    - My Lai massacre (Folder 1: 43)
    - POW-MIA campaigns (Folder 1: 44)
    - Public information and press releases, U.S. military, 1969 (Folder 1: 45)
    - Publications, Republic of Vietnam (South), 1969 and undated (Folder 1: 46)
    - Publications, U.S. Army in Vietnam (Box 1-2)
      - Military units, 1966-1970: Uptight, Winter 1970; The Hurricane, October 1969; Vietnam: A Pictorial; Time magazine insert, "The Negro in Viet Nam," 1967 (Folder 1: 47)
      - Soldiers: "A Pocket Guide to Vietnam," 1962; "Handbook for U.S. Forces in Vietnam," 1968; "RVNAF" (Republic of Viet Nam Armed Forces), 1969; "The Enemy You Face," 1969 (Folder 2: 1)
      - Vietnamese employees: Thông Cảm, December 1969, March 1970, and April 1970 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Publications, U.S. Department of State, about Vietnam, 1961-1970 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Publications, non-governmental, about Vietnam War (Folder 2: 4)
  - Photographs, 1969-1970; 1995-2003 (Box 2-5)
    - 90th Replacement Battalion, U.S. Army, Long Binh, South Vietnam, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - General pictures (Folder 2: 5)
      - Meritorious unit citation, June 1969 (Folder 2: 6)
      - Medical Civic Action Program, near Long Binh (Folder 2: 7)
      - Civic action program with Cao Thai village (Folder 2: 8)
      - Site of communist rocket attack on base, spring 1970 (Folder 2: 9)
      - Monsoon rains (Folder 2: 10)
      - Various, including dispensary, post exchange and unit mascot dog, "Brandy" (Folder 2: 11)
      - 178th Company, Tan Son Nhut airbase, Saigon (Folder 2: 12)
      - 259th Company, processing troops at end of tour of duty (Folder 2: 13)
      - Headquarter Detachment, Long Binh (file 1) (Folder 2: 14)
      - Headquarter Detachment, Long Binh (file 2), includes some photos of 178th Company at Tan Son Nhut airbase (Folder 2: 15)
      - Processing incoming soldiers at Bien Hoa airbase (Folder 2: 16)
    - U.S. Army Vietnam headquarters, Long Binh (Folder 3: 1)
    - Australian military base, Vung Tau (Folder 3: 2)
    - Various scenes, around Long Binh and Saigon, May 1969-April 1970 (Folder 3: 3)
    - U.S. Army quartermaster laundry for soldiers, on road between Long Binh and Saigon (Folder 3: 4)
    - Saigon during wartime, May 1969-April 1970 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Saigon, remains of zoo (Folder 3: 6)
    - Rural Development Corps (Folder 3: 7)
    - Aerial views of Vietnam (Folder 3: 8)
    - Route 1 between Long Binh and Saigon (Folder 3: 9)
    - South Vietnam, government buildings and religious buildings (Folder 3: 10)
    - U.S. Embassy, Saigon and Hanoi, 1969-1995 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Former presidential palaces, Saigon (Ho Chi Minh City), 1995-2003 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Various postcards and photos, 1990s (Folder 3: 13)
    - Cholon, Chinese quarter of Saigon (Ho Chi Minh City), 1969 and 2003 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Hue, postcards and photos, 1995 (Folder 3: 15)
    - War Remnants Museum, Ho Chi Minh City (Saigon), 1995 and 2003 (Folder 3: 16)
    - French colonial influenced architecture and art, 1995-2003 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Chinese influence in Vietnam (Folder 3: 18)
    - War memorials and cemeteries, 1995 and 2003 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Cao Dai religion (Folder 4: 2)
    - War museums, Hue, Hanoi and Danang, 1995 and 2003 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Historic museums, Ho Chi Minh City (Saigon), 1995 and 2003 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Hanoi, 1995 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Booklets from historic museums, 1995-2003, file 1 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Booklets from historic museums, 1995-2003, file 2 (Folder 4: 7)
    - North Vietnamese revolutionary art, 1995-2003 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Vietnam, countryside around Hanoi, Danang, Cuchi, 1995-2003 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Ho Chi Minh City (Saigon), 1995-2003 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Mekong River Delta, 2003 (Folder 4: 11)
    - My Tho (Mekong Delta), 2003 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Pollution and recycling, Mekong Delta, 2003 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Can Tho, car battery recycling shop, 2003 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Can Tho (Mekong Delta), 2003 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Places associated with South Vietnamese president Ngo Dinh Diem (Folder 5: 5)
    - Ho Chi Minh monuments, 1995-2003 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Birth control and AIDS/HIV, 1995-2003 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 5: 8)
- Asia (Other than Vietnam) file, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 5-8)
  Consists of collected materials such as booklets, pamphlets, leaflets, photographs, and sound recordings. Arranged by country.
  - Cambodia and Thailand (Folder 5)
    - Tuol Sleng Prison museum, Phnom Penh (Folder 5: 9)
    - Destroyed buildings, Phnom Penh (Folder 5: 10)
    - Choeung Ek, "Killing Fields" memorial (Folder 5: 11)
    - Vietnamese Victory monument, and other sites in Phnom Penh (Folder 5: 12)
    - Military museum, Siem Reap, Cambodia (Folder 5: 13)
    - Thailand, "Bridge over the River Kwai," Kanchana Buri (Folder 5: 14)
  - China: People's Republic (Box 5)
    - Revolutionary Songs of China (songbook), 1971 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Beijing: Chinese Revolutionary History Museum (Folder 5: 16)
    - Beijing: Anti Japanese Resistance War museum (Folder 5: 17)
    - Nanjing: Nanjing Massacre Memorial Hall, 1996 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Shanghai: Site of the first session of the First Congress of the Chinese Communist Party (Folder 5: 17)
    - Sound recordings (Other Record Cabinet)
      - The East is Red / Sailing the Seas Depends Upon the Helmsman (China Record Company / Guozi Shudian, XM-1031, 33 1/3 r.p.m. sound disc, undated) (Other Record Cabinet)
      - Historical Songs of the Revolution, sung and accompanied by the Central Music Ensemble (China Record Company / Guozi Shudian, XM-1033, 33 1/3 r.p.m. sound disc, undated) (Other Record Cabinet)
      - Two further records, China Record Company / Guozi Shudian, XM-1030 and XM-1037, 33 1/3 r.p.m. sound disc, undated) (Other Record Cabinet)
  - China: Republic of (Taiwan) (Box 6)
    - Quemoy (Kinmen) and Matsu Islands: photographs (Folder 6: 1)
    - Quemoy (Kinmen) and Matsu Islands: postcards and book (Folder 6: 2)
  - Japan (Box 6-7)
    - Tokyo: Yasukuni Shrine, booklets (Folder 6: 3)
    - Tokyo: Yasukuni Shrine, photographs, 1999 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Tokyo: Chidorigafuchi Shrine, photographs, 2004 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Hiroshima: Peace Park and Museum, 1999 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Hiroshima: Peace Museum, temporary exhibit on women in wartime, 1999 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Hiroshima: Peace Park, postcards (Folder 6: 8)
    - Hiroshima: War Memorial, Gokuko Shinto Shrine, 1999 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Nagasaki: Brochures and pamphlets about memorials, museums (Folder 6: 10)
    - Nagasaki: Nagasaki Atomic Bomb Museum, booklets and postcards (Folder 6: 11)
    - Nagasaki: Nagasaki Atomic Bomb Museum, photographs, 1998 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Nagasaki: Urakami Branch Prison memorial, 1998 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Nagasaki: Cathedral ruins, 1998 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Nagasaki: Epicenter Park, 1998 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Nagasaki: Peace Park, statues, 1998 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Posters: Japanese and British, World War II (postcards) (Folder 7: 6)
    - Various Japanese memorials to war dead: Guam, Saipan, Nagoya (Japan), Corregidor (Philippines), 1998-2002 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Various memorials to nationalities killed by Japanese in World War II: Guam, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore, 1994-1998 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Okinawa: various memorials, 1998 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Tokyo: Admiral Togo Shinto shrine, 2004 (Folder 7: 10)
    - Tokyo: General Nogi Shinto shrine, 2004 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Korea (South) (Box 8)
    - Seoul: Monuments regarding history of Japanese colonialism (Folder 8: 1)
    - Korean War: Inchon landing memorials and museums (Folder 8: 2)
    - Republic of Korea Military Museum and Memorial (Folder 8: 3)
    - Demilitarized Zone at Panmunjom (Folder 8: 4)
  - Mongolia (Box 8)
    - Ulan Bator (Box 8)
  - Philippines (Box 8)
    - Corregidor (Box 8)
  - Singapore (Box 8)
- Europe file, 1918-1994 (Box 8-12)
  Contains collected materials such as booklets, pamphlets, leaflets, postcards, and photographs. Arranged by country.
  - Poland (Box 8-9)
    - Anti-Communism, 1918-1990 (Box 8)
    - Polish nationalism, 1914-1918 (Box 8)
    - Battle of Westerplatte, Danzig/Gdansk, 1939 (Box 8)
    - Pawiak Prison Museum, Warsaw (Box 8)
    - Anti-Nazi monuments and memorials (Box 8)
    - Polish victims of World War II (Box 8)
    - Warsaw Uprising, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Anti-Communist monuments, including Katyn Forest (Box 8)
    - World War II memorials, various (Box 8)
    - Polish Government in Exile, London (Box 8)
    - Poland under Communism (Folder 9: 1)
    - Solidarity (Solidarność) monuments (Box 9)
    - Role of the Catholic Church in opposing communism (Box 9)
    - St. Brigid's Church, Gdańsk (Box 9)
    - Father Jerzy Popieluszko (Box 9)
    - Tomb of the Unknown Soldier, Warsaw (Box 9)
    - Polish Military Museum, Warsaw (Box 9)
    - Polish Communist government buildings, Warsaw (Box 9)
    - Changes in Poland after Communist rule (Box 9)
  - Eastern Europe, other (Box 9)
    - Albania (Box 9)
    - Czech Republic, memorial at Lidice (Box 9)
    - Romania, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Germany, East and West (Box 10)
    - Berlin (Box 10)
      - Berlin Wall, checkpoints (Folder 10: 1)
      - Brandenburg Gate, with Quadriga sculpture (Folder 10: 2)
      - Berlin Wall, anti-Soviet graffiti (Folder 10: 3)
      - Berlin Wall, opening of wall, Nov-89 (Folder 10: 4)
      - Berlin Wall, West German graffiti (Folder 10: 5)
      - Television Tower, Alexanderplatz (Folder 10: 6)
      - Neue Wache, Memorial to Victims of Fascism (Folder 10: 7)
      - Military parades and Marxist monuments, 1985-1989 (Folder 10: 8)
      - Statue of Friedrich the Great, Unter den Linden (Folder 10: 9)
      - East German government buildings (Folder 10: 10)
      - 40th anniversary of Soviet victory in World War II (pamphlet), 1985 (Folder 10: 11)
      - East German tourist brochure, Berlin, 1978 (Folder 10: 12)
      - West Berlin, various photographs and postcards (Folder 10: 13)
    - East Germany (Box 10)
      - Transition, 1990-1993 (Folder 10: 14)
      - Transition, Jena, 1988; Leipzig, 1989 (Folder 10: 15)
      - Political souvenirs (Folder 10: 16)
    - Cold War history (Box 11)
      - Berlin Airlift: Postcards, postage stamps, and photographs of Tempelhof Airport (Folder 11: 1)
      - Four Power division of Berlin (Folder 11: 2)
      - Boundary wall dividing East and West Germany, 1990 (Folder 11: 3)
      - Soviet military forces and installations, East Germany (Folder 11: 4)
    - Reunification, 1990 (Box 11)
      - Postcards (Folder 11: 5)
      - Opposition graffiti (Folder 11: 6)
      - Street name changes (Folder 11: 7)
      - SED (former East German ruling party) (Folder 11: 8)
    - Historic monuments and museums (Box 11)
      - Victory Column (Siegessäule), Berlin (Folder 11: 9)
      - Monument to Kaiser Wilhelm I, Koblenz (Folder 11: 10)
      - World War I memorials (Folder 11: 11)
      - Nazi concentration camps (in and outside of Germany) (Folder 11: 12)
      - Memorials to German resistance leaders, World War II / July 20 plot, Berlin (Folder 11: 13)
      - Museum of Unconditional Surrender of Germany, Berlin-Karlshorst (Folder 11: 14)
      - Soviet War memorials (Folder 11: 15)
      - Bitburg cemetery (Folder 11: 16)
      - Exhibits of Weimar-era and anti-Nazi art (Folder 11: 17)
      - Potsdam, Schloss Cecilienhof, site of Potsdam Conference, 1945 (Folder 11: 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - West German attitudes toward America, 1980s (Folder 11: 18)
      - Bonn and its environs, including Konrad Adenauer memorials (Folder 11: 19)
      - Peace movements, West Germany, 1980s (Folder 11: 20)
  - Other European (Box 12)
    - French battlefields from World War I, World War II: Photographs and postcards (Folder 12: 1)
    - Valle de los Caidos (Valley of the Fallen), Spain (Folder 12: 2)
    - Belfast, Northern Ireland: Photographs of murals and military activity (Folder 12: 3)
    - Opposition to nuclear arms, Great Britain, 1984-1990 (Folder 12: 4)
    - Malta, Guide to National War Museum, 1994 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Denmark, Museum of Denmark's Fight for Freedom, 1940-1945 (Folder 12: 6)
    - Bosnia-Herzegovina: Leaflet dropped by NATO planes with humanitarian supplies, 1992 (Folder 12: 7)
    - Karl Marx: Monuments and historic sites, Great Britain and Germany (Folder 12: 8)
    - Georgia: Stalin Museum, Gori, Georgia (Folder 12: 9)
- Miscellany, 1961-2003 (Box 12)
  Includes leaflets, currency, and other collected materials. Arranged by country or organization.
  - Angola: Leaflet promoting Jonas Savimbi, 1992 (Folder 12: 10)
  - Iran: Currency following overthrow of Shah, 1979; and postage stamp honoring assassin of Egyptian president Anwar Sadat, 1982 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Iraq: Photocopies of leaflets used by American and coalition forces against Iraqi Army, 1991 and 2003 (Folder 12: 12)
  - United Nations: Card with rules of conduct of U.N. Peacekeepers (Folder 12: 13)
  - United States: "The Family Fallout Shelter," Department of Defense, Office of Civil Defense, 1961 (Folder 12: 14)